<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cordifragium, or, The sacrifice of a broken heart, open'd, offer'd, own'd, and honour'd. Presented in a sermon at St Pauls London, November 25. 1660. By Francis Walsall D.D. chaplain to his Majesty, and prebendary of St. Peters Westminster.</title>
            <author>Walsall, Francis, d. 1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97070</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1081_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203982</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863728</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863728</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115941</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97070)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115941)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 161:E1081[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cordifragium, or, The sacrifice of a broken heart, open'd, offer'd, own'd, and honour'd. Presented in a sermon at St Pauls London, November 25. 1660. By Francis Walsall D.D. chaplain to his Majesty, and prebendary of St. Peters Westminster.</title>
                  <author>Walsall, Francis, d. 1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Abraham Miller, for John Sherley, at the Golden Pelican in little Brittain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The sacrifice of a broken heart opened, offered, owned, and honoured.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 6", "1660 Feb. 6"; 1 in imprint date crossed out and "0" written in.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115941:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CORDIFRAGI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M,</hi> OR, THE SACRIFICE OF A Broken Heart, Open'd, Offer'd, Own'd, and Honour'd.</p>
            <p>Preſented in a SERMON At <hi>St</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> London, <hi>November</hi> 25. 1660.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Francis Walſall</hi> D. D. Chaplain to his Majeſty, and Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary of St. <hi>Peters Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rabbi David Kimchi,</hi> in Pſalm 51.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Abraham Miller,</hi> for <hi>John Sherley,</hi> at the Golden Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican in little <hi>Brittain.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:115941:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Browne Maior,</hi> 
                  <date>Martis 27<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                     <hi>die</hi> Novembris 1660, <hi>Annoque Reg. Caroli,</hi> &amp;c. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is Ordered that D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Walſall</hi> be from this Court deſired to Print his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> on the laſt Lords, day, before the Lord Maior and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Weld.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115941:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Richard Browne</hi> Knight &amp; Baronett, Lord Maior of the City of <hi>LONDON. WILLIAM BOLTON,</hi> AND <hi>William Peake</hi> Eſquires Sheriffs: ALL The Aldermen, and all the other Officers of that Great and Noble Body.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD hath ſhed ſuch a Glory upon the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of your Undertakings, for the</hi> beſt of Kings and Cauſes, (<hi>for like your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Predeceſſor</hi> Wallworth, <hi>you did not only stab the Rebels, but gave the deaths wound to Rebellion it ſelf) as hath ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed me into ſuch a high and paſsionate veneration of your Lordſhips</hi> Perſon and Parts as well as Place and Power, <hi>that I think it</hi> little leſs than a ſin <hi>to think the leaſt</hi> of your deſires leſs than Commands, <hi>as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears not only in</hi> Preaching this Sacrifice, <hi>but</hi> Sacrificing this Preaching by Printing <hi>this</hi> broken Diſcourſe <hi>of a</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart; <hi>ſetting it up as a mark to be ſhot at with Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisks eyes, and ſhot through with Adders tongues, which are like
<pb facs="tcp:115941:3"/> to do the more ſudden execution, becauſe it comes ſo weak in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, being by your Lordſhips command</hi> delivered <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its time; it is</hi> abortive, <hi>though not</hi> ſtill-born, <hi>and therefore there had bin no great</hi> miſcarriage, <hi>if it had</hi> dyed as ſoon as it was born. <hi>The truth is,</hi> my Lord, <hi>it was a</hi> due debt <hi>to, and deſigned for St.</hi> Peters Weſtminſter (<hi>to which I owe all my little parts and greateſt pains) ſo that I did but rob</hi> Peter <hi>to pay</hi> Paul, <hi>in Preaching it to you; as a puniſhment of which guilt, I might juſtly fear a</hi> ſeverer ſentence from your Bench, <hi>then that it ſhould be</hi> judged to be preſſed to Life. <hi>But ſince your</hi> Lordſhip <hi>and your</hi> Court <hi>will have it ſo, be it ſo,</hi> let it live, <hi>let it live, by, and for, and in, and with, and within, and without you and them, that is in your lives.</hi> The life of the Sermon is the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of the life: we may Preach well, but it is you that muſt make the good Sermons, <hi>by</hi> making the <hi>Sermons good, by Preaching the</hi> uſe <hi>of our</hi> Doctrine <hi>in your</hi> Lives. <hi>Then are Sermons</hi> delivered to the hearers in a Goſpel-way, when<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 17.</note> the hearers are delivered to (or into) the Sermons. <hi>This is the ſenſe of the Apoſtle,</hi> Ye have obeyed from the heart that form of Doctrine which was delivered to you: <hi>it is in the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to which ye were delivered. The</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cornelius A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa</hi> in <hi>Occultâ Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophiâ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hebrew Doctors ſay, that there is a ſtone in every man, which they call Luz, of ſuch an unpenetrable, indiſſoluble hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that it daſtards and deſies the fury and force of all the Elements, as being the Garriſon, that defends the being of the Individuum; its immortall ſeed, and the life out of which man ſprings up again in his intire nature to the harveſt of the Reſurrection: and the Poet ſeignes, we are made of ſtones,</hi> Inde genus durum ſumus—. <hi>This is the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of every natural man; and thoſe that be ſtill in their</hi> puris; <hi>or rather</hi> impuris naturalibus, <hi>in their natural</hi> hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart, <hi>I know will not</hi> like a Diſcourſe of a broken
<pb facs="tcp:115941:3"/> heart, <hi>becauſe they are not</hi> like it: <hi>for</hi> likeneſs <hi>breeds</hi> liking: <hi>and they are not</hi> like it: <hi>at leaſt they are not it, that is,</hi> broken hearted, <hi>and they that are whole, as they need not, ſo they care not for the Phyſician—. Whereas to thoſe whoſe hearts were broken before this Sermon, or by it, it will be as pleaſing a ſervice to their</hi> eyes, <hi>as to their</hi> ears, <hi>and to both, as a broken heart is a</hi> pleaſing ſacrifice <hi>to God. But be it what it will, what ever it is, it is</hi> your Lordſhips, <hi>for not only the ſeaſon, but the Subject of this Diſcourſe owes it ſelf wholly to</hi> your Lordſhip: <hi>For I had pitched upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Theme that had ſpoke more home, and more handſome to the Times, had I not bin taken off by</hi> your Lordſhips <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, intimating your deſire not to meddle with</hi> Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c. I muſt needs ſay, it was a ſharp Sarcaſme of</hi> Luther <hi>to his querulous and criticall</hi> Melancthon, Deſinat Philippus eſſe Rex mundi, <hi>Let God, and thoſe that governe the world under him, alone with governing the world under them; and it was a great truth, though ſpoken by him, that was the eldeſt Sonne of the Father of lies, that deified Swine</hi> Mahomet, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>God is his own Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the works, that is eminently the Reiglement of the world, and therefore the ſame Impoſtor calls God</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Dominus Mundi, <hi>and yet the ſame God hath given a large Commiſsion to his Ambaſſadors in Caſes where the Laws of man are</hi> built upon, <hi>or</hi> built up to <hi>the Laws of God, as all ſhould be. But I will not ſwell an Epiſtle into a Treatiſe on that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; it is enough, that</hi> your Lordſhip <hi>ſees I did comply with your deſires in it, even though the times were ſo happily fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as to afford a large crop of excellent matter, that would</hi> prodeſſe &amp; delectare, <hi>to entertain you with profit and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the bleſſed change of Governement, from the</hi> worſt of
<pb facs="tcp:115941:4"/> Tyrants, <hi>to the</hi> beſt of Princes: <hi>And I the rather choſe to reſolve my ſelf into the obedience of your</hi> Lordſhips <hi>dictates, becauſe the laſt piece I Printed was,</hi> The Bowing the Hearts of Subjects to their Soveraigne, <hi>and I could hardly do leſſe (ſince it did not goe before it) than follow it, with</hi> Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heart in ſacrifice to God: <hi>For</hi> that heart is never ſweetly bowed in ſubjection to the King, that is not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly broken in ſacrifice to God.</p>
            <p>Your Lordſhip <hi>hath the honour of aeternizing your name, by being an Active Inſtrument in digging the Church and State from under thoſe heaps of Ruine and Rubbiſh, the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and Covetouſneſs of a Popular Tyranny, had long buryed them under, in the bleſſed Reſtoring of his</hi> Sacred Majeſty <hi>to his</hi> Suffering Subjects, <hi>for which Generations to come ſhall bleſſe your memory. Go on,</hi> my Lord, <hi>go on to plant whole Groves of Laurel, to crown your Self, your City, your Poſterity with unperiſhable glories, by a Generous and Charitable Reflection upon that Aged heap of Ruines, once the wonder of the world, and the Crowne of this Queen of Iſlands, I mean the Church of St.</hi> Paul, <hi>in a Canton of which this Sermon was delivered to you. When I firſt came into that eminent Monument of</hi> Ancient Piety, (<hi>and</hi> Moderne Impiety) <hi>for Gods ſervice and yours, though I may be eaſily imagined to have bin ſo full of the great work I was to do, that I had little roome to entertaine other thoughts; yet I muſt ingenuouſly confeſſe, that ſadding Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject (which looked like the Picture and Emblem of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>in its late ruinous poſture) broke through all my other notions (that were then upon wing and fluttered to get out) and ſtormd my hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, till at length it retreated to my eyes, and went out where it came in with a wet Prayer in</hi> Davids <hi>language,</hi> Pſalm 102. 13, 14. Ariſe ô Lord and have mercy upon Zion, for the time is come
<pb facs="tcp:115941:4"/> that thou have mercy upon her, yea the ſet time is come, and why? thy ſervants think upon her ſtones, and it pitties them to ſee her in the duſt. <hi>Pardon my Zeale</hi> (my Lord) <hi>if it ſwallow down my Diſcretion, it is for the Houſe of God, and that eat up</hi> David <hi>and the Sonne of</hi> David: <hi>I owe my Birth and Breeding to the Neighbourhood of that Mother-Church (to me in a more eminent way) I have many precious Pawns depoſited under her deare walls, beſides my living Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, that I muſt ſay with</hi> David, For my Brethren and<note place="margin">Pſalm 122. 8.</note> Companions ſake I wiſh thee proſperity: <hi>And ſo I know doth</hi> your Lordſhip, <hi>and let the world know it too, by a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable lending your ſucceſſefull hand to raiſe up our Aged Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the Duſt. It is a labour worthy ſuch a</hi> Hercules <hi>to purge that</hi> Augaean <hi>Stable, it is ſad to call it ſo, but it was ſo, and bleſſed be God we may ſay it was ſo. You know when a</hi> Den of Thieves <hi>made it a</hi> Stable for Horſes: <hi>and ſo or worſe they would have uſed all our Churches:</hi> They would have deſtroyed all the Houſes of God in the Land, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed them at leaſt from being any longer Houſes of God, at leaſt theſe Mother-Churches, to ſpoile the breed, and to that end they ſaid, let us take the Houſes of God in poſſeſsion, they ſaid, that is, it was reſolved upon the Queſtion: but God repealed their Act (if it be worth that name) and turnd their Ordinance upon themſelves, and as it follows there, made them like a wheele, turnd it from</hi> Regno <hi>to</hi> ſum<note place="margin">Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 83. 12, 13.</note> ſine Regno. <hi>And who knows but that as God hath bin plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to honour you with a great part in this glorious work of Reſtoring the King to his Houſe, but that it is intended by it, to prompt you to reſtore God to his Houſe, the Houſe of God to the God of the Houſe. Let me ſay to</hi> your Lordſhip <hi>as</hi> Mordecay <hi>ſaid to</hi> Eſther, who knowes whether thou art come to this honour for ſuch a time as this? <hi>Never was</hi> Lord Maior <hi>wellcomed into his Office with more generall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacrity and acclamations, which as they</hi> did loudly ſpeak the
<pb facs="tcp:115941:5"/> good you had done, ſo they did lovingly beſpeak the good they would have you do. <hi>And therefore let me be ſo bold to ſay to</hi> your Lordſhip <hi>as</hi> David <hi>did to his Son</hi> Solomon,<note place="margin">1 Chron. 22. 16.</note> 
               <hi>who was deſigned for ſuch work, the building of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> ariſe therefore and be doing, and the Lord ſhall be with thee. <hi>You cannot want incouragement, for beſides that, the wiſhes of Prince and People concenter in it, God hath bleſt</hi> London <hi>with a prudent</hi> Biſhop, <hi>cut out as it were for all manner of</hi> Church-work. <hi>Therefore I will ſay no more, but, that, when I ſee</hi> two ſuch benign ſtarres in conjunction and vertical over this great City, <hi>I cannot but</hi> propheſie (<hi>prognoſticate is too fallible a term) great bleſsings, and I pray that I may be a true Prophet, as I am truely</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Lordſhips <hi>moſt humble Servant in the work of our great Maſter,</hi> Francis Walſall.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 
                  <date>Jan. 1. 1660. <hi>Juxta Comput. Eccleſiae Anglis.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 1. in Margin, after <hi>Job</hi> 16. 14. add <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>confractione coram confractione,</hi> with one breach in the ſight of another, like the waves of the Sea, one upon the neck of another, or like his own meſſengers of ill news, one upon the heeles of another, <hi>p. 3. l.</hi> 15. againſt <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 10. in the Margin add theſe Verſes,
<q>
                  <l>Tunc piceae mactantur oves, proſectaque partim</l>
                  <l>Pectora, per medios partim gerit obvius Idmon.</l>
                  <l>Val<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Flac. Arg. l. 2. Vid. plura in Analect. ſacra doctiſſimi Doughteij noſtri.</l>
               </q> p. 8. line 15. r. <hi>foyles,</hi> p. 10. l. 7. r. <hi>lies,</hi> p. 11. l. 15. r. <hi>broken into two pieces,</hi> p. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> l. 22. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ibid. l. 30. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and ibib. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 18. in Marg. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 29. l. 12. after <hi>above,</hi> r. <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. 11. l. 13. r. <hi>deep,</hi> p. 34. l. 10. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 38. l. 2. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 38. l. 19. r. <hi>his grace is his meal.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115941:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSAL. 51. 17.</bibl>
               <q>The Sacrifices of God are a broken ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, a broken and contrite heart, O God thou wilt not deſpiſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E have had our ſhare in <hi>broken</hi> and <hi>breaking</hi> Times, the Lord hath <hi>broken</hi> us, as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, with<note place="margin">Job. 16. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Breach upon Breach; every thing has been broken but that which ſhould be, our hearts: and though we think we have now a cleare Proſpect into the end of our miſeries, and the healing of our <hi>Breaches,</hi> by this <hi>miracle</hi> of <hi>mercy,</hi> the happy return of the <hi>Soverainge repairer</hi> of our <hi>Breaches,</hi> and reſtorer of paths to dwell in:<note place="margin">Eſ. 58. 12. Jer. 14. 19.</note> yet we have heard of thoſe that looked for <hi>healing,</hi> and behold <hi>trouble.</hi> Whether the <hi>great Phyſician</hi> will at this time make a thorow <hi>cure</hi> of our <hi>ruptures</hi> I cannot divine, but yet I may <hi>ſafely</hi> as <hi>ſadly</hi> ſay, if he doe not, we may thank our ſelves for it, we may <hi>thank</hi> our own <hi>thankleſſneſs;</hi> if we be <hi>any more broken,</hi> it is becauſe we <hi>are no more broken;</hi> as we have been <hi>broken ſo much, becauſe we have not been broken enough,</hi> we ſtill want this Breaking in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115941:6"/> Text, Heart-breaking: for all our other <hi>outward break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> we are <hi>heart-wholl</hi> ſtill (as we uſe to ſay) our hearts are not broken, our hearts are indeed <hi>ſadly divided,</hi> but not <hi>ſavingly broken:</hi> we are not brok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en for <hi>ſin,</hi> we are not broken from <hi>ſin;</hi> but like the ſmiths anvill we are rather <hi>harden'd</hi> than broken by all our <hi>ſtrokes,</hi> we are <hi>word-proofe,</hi> and <hi>ſword<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe;</hi> we neither heare the <hi>rod of the Word,</hi> nor the <hi>Word of the rod;</hi> we laugh under the <hi>rod</hi> and the proud fleſh grow's under the <hi>Sword;</hi> we are not ſo much as <hi>pricked at the heart,</hi> if we were, we ſhould be in their poſture, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 37. When they were <hi>pricked at the heart</hi> they ſaid unto <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, men and bretheren what ſhall we doe? But doe we ſo? ſurely no; we doe not ſo becauſe we are not ſo; were our hearts <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>throwghly</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken we would make more haſt to the great Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician who is onely able to bind up the broken heart, who healeth the broken in heart and giveth<note place="margin">Pſ. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 30.</note> them medicine to heale their ſicknes. But I will not anticipat an application with a preface: only give me leave to breath out a ſhort ejaculation, and ſo to our work: the Lord give us broken hearts, break us that we may be broken; and breake us that we may not be broken, and give us contrite ſpirits that we be not reſerved to fall under the weight of that ſad and antient Porpheſie <hi>Conterendj</hi>—<note n="*" place="margin">Polychr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>icon</note> that we may be <hi>contriti,</hi> that we be not <hi>Conterendi.</hi>—But to the words <hi>Beza.</hi> (and our learned <hi>Fuller</hi> approves his judgment) ſayes that the Apoſtles <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fulleri miſcell. p. 224. lib.</hi> 3. 2 Tim. 2. 15.</note> rightly dividing the word of truth, is a meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phore that alludes to the Prieſts dividing the Sacrifices
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115941:6"/> under the Law, and probably enough, becauſe in preaching the word the Miniſter chooſeth and ſingles out a particular Text out of all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ock of Scripture to be conſecrated for that uſe as a Sacrifice, by divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it part for God, and part for his people, and to the people their due ſhare in their due ſeaſon: therefore the buſineſſe of my Text being Sacrifices, I ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen it as they uſed to open the Sacrifices under the Law, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is the meaning of St <hi>Pauls, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heb.</hi> 4. 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. All things are naked and <hi>open</hi> (ſo we read it) but it is rather <hi>opened</hi> as they uſed to open the Sacrifices of the Law, throwgh the middle, from the neck downward, as we ſee it cleared in the practiſe of <hi>Abraham. Gen.</hi> 15. 10. And he took the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices and divide them in the mid'ſt, and layd each piece one againſt another, and this beareth a huge proportion with our Text: for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an iron ſinew in theneck, and a ſtone in the heart ſpeak the ſame thing in Scripture, and muſt be both alike Sacrificed and broken: ſo ſhall I Sacrifice my Text by ſo breaking of it, that is juſt in the midſt, into two parts, and lay the the parts one againſt another thus.</p>
            <p>The two parts are. 1. Sacrifices offered. 2. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices owned and honoured.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sacrifices offered; the Sacrifices of God, that is offered to God, are a broken ſpirit and a contrite heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sacrifices owned and honoured a broken heart and contrite ſpirit (for I muſt put both into both) God will not deſpiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115941:7"/>1. Sacrifices offered, the Sacrifices offered to God, <hi>a broken</hi> ſpirit, and <hi>a broken</hi> and contrite heart: here are two participles in the Hebrew which make two weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Epithets upon which lies the whole ſtreſſe and burden of the Text, and they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the one ſignifies to break <hi>whole things all of a piece,</hi> and the other ſignifies <hi>to breake hard things all to pieces,</hi> that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a word of a higher ſtreine, to break a thing to powder. So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. 5. They break in pieces thy people, O Lord, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. So <hi>Job</hi> 19. 2. How long will ye vex my ſoul and break me in pieces with words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Atteretis me,</hi> will ye grinde me to powder? So that put both together and you have here Heart, a whole Heart broken in pieces, and a Heart, a hard Heart beaten to powder: things muſt be whole or they cannot be broken to pieces; and they muſt be hard, or they cannot be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to powder: ſo that this breaking, this beating ſpeakes violence, the macerations and martyrizati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of repentance, that holy violence, and force that Heaven is taken with. Therefore a Heart ſo uſed is called a broken and a contrite heart. Thus it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a ſoul truly humbled, beaten, and broken and ground to powder; in this ſenſe it is applyed to Chriſt, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 53. 10. Yet it pleaſed the Lord to bruiſe him, he hath put him to grief, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to break him in pieces; thus in the ſame ſenſe you finde <hi>contrite</hi> and <hi>humble</hi> put together twice in one Text, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 57. 15. For thus ſaith the high and lofty one that inhabits eternity, whoſe name is holy; I dwell in the high and holy place, with him alſo that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115941:7"/> to revive the ſpirit of the humble and to revive the ſpirit of the contrite ones: A broken heart then is a ſpirit duly and deeply humbled under the ſenſe of ſin for the School gives a diſtinction between Attrition: and Contrition: the object of Attrition is the evil of puniſhment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the object Contrition is the evil of ſin. So that a broken heart is a heart bleeding un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſight and ſenſe of, and ſorrow for ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Part is the Sacrifices owned and honoured, and to this you riſe in ſtate by three ſtepps. 1. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices. 2. Sacrifices of God. 3. Such Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as God will not deſpiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sacrifices in the Plural Number, all Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as if all other ſacrifices were either nothing at all to this, or without this, or all in all in this, of a broken heart: when we beate or breake hard things into minute parts or powder, we call it the flower of it: a broken heart is <hi>ſlos cordis</hi> the flower of the heart and that is the <hi>Flower</hi> of all Sacrifices, and the finer the flower (that is the more beaten or broken) the fitter offering for God. Thus truly <hi>pulvis ſanctus,</hi> is <hi>pulvis cardia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> the Heart pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is the holy powder. Beſides the ordinary Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe for common uſes, the fineſt and fitteſt for Gods<note place="margin">Rev. 2 17. 1 Pet. 3. 41.</note> ſervice and ſacrifices; the Phyſicians call <hi>Manna thuris,</hi> the <hi>Broken</hi> and Contrite heart is <hi>Manna cordis,</hi> the Hidden <hi>Manna</hi> of the Hidden man of the heart: the Broken heart is not only for all ſervices, but for all Sacrifices, nay is all Sacrifices. Every ragg, every ſhiver, every graine, every atome of the Broken Heart is a whole burnt offering, nay a <hi>hecatomb</hi> of Sacrifices.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115941:8"/>2. The ſatcrifices of God, it is a frequent Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-phraſe to raiſe the price of things of excellence and eminence above others by adding the name of God to them, as the waters of God, the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of God, the Cedars of God, and ſo here the Sacrifices of God, that is, the moſt excellent ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. We have it in the new Teſtament, The Peace of God, that is, ſuch a Peace as do's not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſe other Peaces, but all underſtanding <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 7. But I conceive there is more in it than ſo, the ſacrifices of God that is, the ſacrifices that God do's moſt owne and honour and is moſt intereſted in: as if he had ſaid, all other ſacrifices are but the ſacrifices of men: Bullocks and Rammes, Sheepe and Goats: Turtles and Pigeons; Beaſts and Birds; Fruits and Flowers; theſe were but the ſacrifices of men; but my ſon give me thy heart ſais God, that is the<note place="margin">Prov. 23. 26.</note> ſacrifice he only delights in: all the reſt without this are an abomination to him; theſe alone are the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of God, for here as he did to <hi>Abraham,</hi> God<note place="margin">Ezek. 36. 26.</note> himſelf provides the Sacrifice for himſelf, for he alone that is the <hi>heart-maker</hi> is <hi>the heart-breaker:</hi> it is Gods prerogative royall to take out the heart of ſtone and put in a heart of fleſh: it is no wonder if he liks his own choice and accepts what himſelf provides. He is the feaſt, the gueſt, the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and therefore, ſure, he will not deſpiſe his own cheere, and tha is thet</p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Step by which we riſe to Gods owning and honouring theſe ſacrifices; that God will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe them.</p>
            <p>You will ſay this is but a very thin and low and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115941:8"/> ſlight way of honouring a thing not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer that under this lower phraſe of owning them, that God will not deſpiſe them, is to be underſtood Gods choiſeſt way of accepting and hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouring them in the higheſt degree, as if he had ſaid as the Apoſtle ſai's of that other ſacrifice of doing good and diſtributing. <hi>Heb,</hi> 13. 16. With ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed, ſo <hi>v.</hi> 17. The ſame chapt. Obey them that have the Rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you. &amp;c. For it is profitable for you: this is but a ſhort expreſſion, and reaches not home to the Apoſtles meaning; for according to his own Doctrine it is not only profitable to do it, but it is damnable not to doe it, becauſe it is to be done for Chriſts ſake and conſience ſake: ſo 1 <hi>Theſ. 5. 20. Deſpiſe not prophecying,</hi> here is our word again; the Apoſtles meaning here is that we ſhould honour prophecying, though he ſai's only deſpiſe it not, and though this Text in the loweſt ſenſe has been ſo long too much deſpiſed (even under high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes of doing it honour (yet, certainly, he that would have honour and double Honour given to the Miniſters for their workes ſake; would not have leſſe given to the work it ſelf. Thus theſe ſacrifices God will not deſpiſe, that is God will accept them, own them, honour them above all other ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices in the world.</p>
            <p>The reſult of all theſe clearings of the ſenſe is this, that a Broken heart is the moſt acceptable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God, which he moſt own's moſt honours. A principle that needs improving more than prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115941:9"/> and therefore the wheels and hinges my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhall move upon ſhall be theſe four only.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What a broken and a contrite heart is.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Some <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Characters or rules by which a man may be able to paſs a judgment upon his heart, whether it be truly broken.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some whets to ſharpen your deſires and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors after a broken heart.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Some arguments to quicken your <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Caution</hi> that you give not over your paines, till you be ſure the work is done; that when all is done, you be not deceived in this important duty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is a broken and a contrite heart? and here becauſe <hi>Contraria inter ſe poſita magis eluceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt,</hi> Contraries are the beſt fyles to ſet off and to ſet out one another. I will pave my way to a <hi>Broken heart</hi> out of the qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry of a <hi>hard</hi> Heart: you may pleaſe to know then that there is a threefold hardneſs of heart.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A naturall. 2. An acquired. 3. A Judicial hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A naturall hardneſs of heart which every man brings into the world with him: we are all born Prodigies and Monſters with ſtones in our boſomes neather mill-ſtones in our hearts: thus the Apoſtle characters the Gentiles, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 18. Having the underſtanding darkned, being alienated from the life of God through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the blindneſs of their hearts, (ſo we reade it) but it ſhould be, becauſe of the hardneſſe of their hearts: ſo ſaies the margin, and ſo ſhould have ſaid the Text, for, beſides that blindneſſe is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115941:9"/> in the words before, <hi>having the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding darkned,</hi> and the words following <hi>through the ignorance that is in them,</hi> is in the Greeke, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Which very expreſſion you have tranſlated hardneſs of heart elſwhere. <hi>viz, Mark. 3. 5. Being grieved for the hardneſs of their hearts</hi> And yet it is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. And that it muſt be <hi>hardneſs</hi> and not blindneſs the derivation of the word ſpeakes. For the Greeks derive <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from the ſtone <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the nature of which is to harden by the ſticking to of viſcous and glutinous waters, as the ſtone hardens in the Reines and Bladder. And ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifies hardneſs, and is by a kind of Catachreſticall metaphore uſed for thoſe <hi>tophi</hi> or hard ſwellings, of purulent matter grown into a callous or brawny ſubſtance in the joynts or Lunges, as <hi>Ariſt.</hi> tells us in his <hi>hiſtoria animalium</hi> and that (with all reverence to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the learned Tranſlators) this is not my Conjecture only, but the ſenſe of the Spirit. I ſhall give you a Text where both theſe words are uſed in their proper ſenſe diſtinctly, <hi>Joh. 12. 40. He hath blinded their eyes, and hardened their hearts, that they ſhould not ſee with their eyes, nor underſtand with their hearts,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he hath blinded and he hath hardened. This is that naturall hardneſs of heart which I am ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off, not ſo much blindneſs as a Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and effect of it, a hardneſs that grow's from blindneſs: it is hard as well as blind, nay hard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe blind (to lappe up both in one Engliſh word) it may be <hi>ſtone-blind,</hi> for it ſpeakes an affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115941:10"/> ignorance, blindneſs in ſpite of <hi>light and ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There is an acquired hardneſs. <hi>Heb. 3. 13. leaſt any of you be hardned through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfullneſs of ſin.</hi> Sin cheates us into <hi>cuſtome</hi> and cuſtome out of conſcience. Sin is like ſome waters that have a naturall <hi>petrifying</hi> quality, and will harden any thing into ſtone that lays any time in them. Let a godly manly in any ſin any time, neglect duty and give himſelf a looſe to the world, and he ſhall ſee in how ſhort a time a <hi>cruſt</hi> will grow over his heart, a <hi>ſcirrus</hi> upon his conſcience; that will make him both unwilling to duty: and unweildy in duty: his faith will take winde and be apt to taint when he keeps not cloſe to God in duty: <hi>Delicata res eſt ſpiritus ſanstus;</hi> the ſpirit of God is a dainty tender thing and ſoone ſnibd; no marvell therefore if that <hi>heart be hard</hi> that has driven away the <hi>ſoftning ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There is a judiciall hardneſs of heart; a hardneſs that comes or rather is ſent, upon the heart by the juſt judgment of God, to puniſh thoſe other hardeneſſes: the Lord does many times turne (as it was reported whether true or falſe I know not) our hearts (as he did the people in <hi>Tripoly</hi>) into ſtone in judgment: as we ſee <hi>Eſ. 63. 17. O Lord why haſt thou made us to erre from thy ways, and hardened our hearts from thy feare?</hi> O this is the ſaddeſt of all judgments when God does (not only puniſh ſin with ſin, whip one ſin with another, but) puniſh putrifacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with petrifaction by hardening us in ſin <hi>ſteel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the conſcience and <hi>braſſing</hi> the countenance
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115941:10"/> not only to <hi>continuance in ſin;</hi> but <hi>confidence in ſinning:</hi> O a <hi>ſeared conſcience</hi> is a <hi>ſealed condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What is a Broken Heart then? that comes next having done with a hard one. When a thing is broken it is broken into ſome parts greater or leſſer, more or fewer: what then is this Heart broken into? to give you all the little parts and <hi>Atomes,</hi> a broken heart is crumbled into, were a taske as endleſs (and needleſs) as that <hi>Venus</hi> (in <hi>Apuleius</hi>) laid upon <hi>Pſyche,</hi> to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and diſtinguiſh a heape of petit graines. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will only give you the prime leading parts, the leſſer, inferiour, and more ſubordinate only, as they offer themſelves in our way.</p>
            <p>This broken Heart then is broken into pieces.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Low thoughts of himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. High thoughts of God.</p>
            <p>Theſe parts (to ſpeake properly) though the heart be broken into, yet it is not made of: for as we ſay of a line, that it is divided into, not made of points; ſo this heart though bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into, is not made up of theſe pieces, as ingredients; they <hi>divide,</hi> not <hi>conſtitute;</hi> they doe not make it, but rather ſpeake it broken; for the bloud of Chriſt alone is the <hi>Balme of Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead,</hi> or rather the <hi>Gilead of Balme,</hi> that alone makes up a broken heart.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then what are theſe low thoughts of a mans ſelfe, into which it is broken? Here I ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g the favour of you to helpe me out a little with your fancy: the Prophet ſpeaking of God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115941:11"/> 
               <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 18. Saies <hi>I have heard Ephraim bemoan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe thus.</hi> Suppoſe now you were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the hanging, and heard <hi>Job, David, Peter, Paul, Auguſtin, Anſelm, Jerom, Bernard,</hi> or any other humbled Saint of God, at his confeſſion: what doe you think, would ſuch mortified ſoules, ſuch broken hearts breake out into? I will head a few ſhort hints of a Broken Hearts, low thoughts of himſelfe in ſeven broken ſighs; thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Broken heart bleeds out a ſigh over his emptineſs of all good, in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> complaint <hi>Rom. 7. 18. I know that in me (that is in my fleſh) dwels no good thing.</hi> Strangers that are at a diſtance from me, and know me not, <hi>intus &amp; in cute,</hi> or <hi>in cute</hi> only, my outſide, only, may perhaps cry me up for <hi>Piety, parts, and pains;</hi> perhaps thoſe that have any <hi>Relation</hi> or <hi>Obligation</hi> to me, may finde out a prety <hi>Inventory of goods</hi> in me to praiſe in their judgment. But O the Lord knows, and I know my ſelf, and ſo would others too, did they know me as well as I doe, or ſhould, and (I thank God) would know my ſelf, that there is no good in me, but that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee and weepe the evill that is in me: and that is his</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sigh, not only that I am empty of all good, but full of all evill; and here he breaks out into la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, not only for all the evils that have broke out in him, but for the evils that lye hid and dormant in him, and may break out, his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent as well as his patent evils.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115941:11"/>1. For the ils that have appeared in him, O! ſaies the Broken heart, the Devill could not ſuggeſt, nor the damned in hell commit worſe evils then I have done; and here he lanches into that black ſea of ſin, and runs over thoſe three bead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolls of evils. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. From verſe 29. to the 32. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9. 10. And that catalogue of the works of the fleſh <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. from verſe, 19. to the 21. I have ſinned ſo and ſo and ſo. The Sun in Heaven doth not warm, nor the fire in hell doth not burn a more falſe, filthy, foule, baſe, debauched ſinner than I am: Gods mercy never ſaved, Gods juſtice never damned a more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull, unfaithfull, unfruitfull, wretch than wretched I.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For his latent evils, for his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 2. The hidden things of diſhoneſty, or rather the hidden things of ſhame; ſo the Greek, and more properly; his ſecret ſins, ſins that are ſo hidden from the world, that they are almoſt hidden from himſelf, though he cannot with <hi>Caeſar</hi> call every Souldier that fight's againſt his ſoule in this formidable Army, that quarters in his heart, by name: yet he has diſcovered a vaſt Army of corruption in ambuſh there, that makes him cry out upon that diſcovery with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul Rom. 7. 24. O wretched man that I am who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death?</hi> I have a body of ſin in me; ſin in a corporation, not only ſin in armes, but ſin in an Army, ſin in a body, ſin in a Garriſon, ſin in a ſtrong hold; I have all the ſins in the world in my baſe heart. Philoſophy may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115941:12"/> flatter me that I have the ſeeds of all vertves in me, but I ſee that I have the ſeeds of all ſins in me, even of that fearfull ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt: And that theſe ſins have not broken out into open defiance againſt God and man, it is no thank to any goodneſs in me, but the goodneſs of God alone; it is nothing but the over-ruling power of Gods grace that has kept me from being outwardly and openly, as vilely wicked as the baſeſt, the beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeſt of ſinners. O I am a den of wild beaſts, a bed of Serpents, a cage of uncleane Birds, a ſinke of ſin: I am all toade, all beaſt, all Divell: and if God have caged up theſe birds, charmed theſe ſerpents, tyed up theſe wilde beaſts that they have not broken out to the loathing of the world; I am beholding to the goodneſs of God, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for that little good I have done, but for the great evils I have not done.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He breaths a ſigh, not only over his bondage to ſin, but to the creatures: who was ever more inſnared with dotage on the creatures than I? how am I brought under the power of mean and low things; things which God has deſigned for no higher ends than to be helps and ſeaſonings and ſweetenings of my Pilgrimage, as meats and drinks, relations, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> would not be ſo; he would not be brought under the power of any 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 12. But ſeverall creatures are Princes and Gods over me: and many times when I have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of my duty to doe the will of God, and have been willing and ready to doe it, and even ſetting upon the work, theſe petty Divinities,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115941:12"/> theſe creature-deitys have exerciſed ſuch a rugged Empire over my heart, that I durſt not obey God, becauſe I durſt not diſobey them, nay I have choſen rather to obey them than God: O what a ſlave has my Idolatry to a little painted fleſh, or ſhining earth made me? It has not only unchriſtianed me, but unmaned me, befooled me, bebeaſted me, bedrudged me, bedeviled me.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He ſighs out his unworthineſſe of any of Gods dealings with him: his unworthineſſe. 1. Of any mercy from God. 2. Of any relation to God. 3. Of any Correction by God.</p>
            <p n="1">1 He ſees his unworthineſſe of any Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to him. <hi>Jacob</hi> breathes out the language of a broken heart. <hi>Gen. 32. 10. I am leſs than the leaſt of thy mercies.</hi> q. d. I have done my beſt (that is) my worſt to ſin away thy mercies by ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with, and againſt thy mercies; I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that thou ſhouldeſt curſe thy mercies and blaſt thy bleſſings to me, or take them from me <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> I have leſſened my ſelf from thy mercies, and made my ſelf unworthy of them: <hi>I am leſs than the leaſt of all thy mercies.</hi> And yet thou art pleaſed to continue thy greateſt to me: thy mercy is my miracle, that thou canſt find in thy heart to doe any good to a thing that is ſo bad, ſo baſe, ſo wretched as I am. <hi>Lord what is man that thou art mindfull of him?</hi> Pſ. 8. 4. It is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> wretched weake miſerable man, ſo the word ſignifies, and I the moſt miſerable of all men? Lord what
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115941:13"/> am I miſerable ſinfull I, that thou ſhouldeſt yet looke upon me?</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſees himſelf unworthy of any relation to God. Lord (ſayes the broken heart) I pretend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to be thy child and that thou art my father: I ſay our father with them that underſtand it but<note place="margin">Deut. 32. 5. Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 37 32</note> little, but none deſerves it leſs: O I prophane that holy prayer of my Saviour: I blaſpheme that grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous name, and blaſt that glorious Relation: I thy ſon? no; no, my ſin is not the ſpot of thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: is this thy ſons coate that is beſmeared and ſpotted with uncleanneſſe, rolled in bloud, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colored with ſchimes, ſects, errors, hereſie, diviſions, anger, malice, ſlander, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Spaniards that called themſelves the ſons of God, when they baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whole ſholes of Indians in their own bloud, had as juſt a title to thy ſonſhip as I: if I be thy ſon, I am ſuch a ſon as <hi>Abſolom,</hi> a rebellious child, that run that ſword atilt at his fathers breſt in a horrid rebellion, that came newlyreeking out of the bloud and bowells of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that tongue, thoſe hands, I ſin againſt man with, I fight againſt God with. If I be a ſon I am a <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> of whom their father ſaid after they had murdered the King and the people of <hi>Sichem,</hi> ye<note place="margin">Gen. 34. 30.</note> have made me to ſtink among the inhabitants of the Land, the name of God has been blaſphemed through me, therefore according to thine own Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,<note place="margin">John. 8. 44.</note> my father is the Devil, for his workes only I have done: no, no; I am not thy ſon <hi>I have ſinned againſt heaven and before thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy ſon.</hi> Luk. 15. 18.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115941:13"/>3. Nay Lord I am not only unworthy any mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from thee, or any relation to thee; but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of any correction by thee, as holy <hi>Job</hi> in the midſt of his heart-breaking expoſtulates it with God. <hi>Job 7. 17, 18. What is man that thou ſhouldeſt magnify him? and that thou ſhouldeſt ſet thine heart upon him? And that thou ſhouldeſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit him every morning and try him every moment!</hi> I am worthy indeed of of puniſhment to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but not to correction: <hi>Indignus ſum quem vel percutias,</hi> as he ſaid: what God ſais to proud ſinners; <hi>Eſ. 1. 6. Why ſhould ye be ſtrick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en any more? ye will revolt more and more:</hi> That a broken heart ſayes to himſelf; why ſhould the Lord take the paines to chaſten me? why ſhould he looſe a correction upon me? I am nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worthy to be ſtroked nor to be ſtruck; neither Gods <hi>Jacobs</hi> hands, his ſofter hands of mercy, nor his <hi>Eſaus</hi> hands, his rougher hands of juſtice could doe any good upon me.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He ſighs over his own inability (as well as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs) to draw near to God in any duty. O ſaies the broken heart, the time was, I thought my ſelf ſome body, nay like S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty man,</hi> that I could doe all things, I thought<note place="margin">Phil. 4. 13.</note> I could have heard, read, prayed, lived up to means and mercies, lain at the foot of God in ſubmiſſion, when I lay under his hand in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and in ſome meaſure have performed all the duties the Lord requires of me; but now I feele my ſelf fit for nothing, but to ſin againſt him. I doe not <hi>live the life of faith,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115941:14"/> 
               <hi>I cannot breath the breath of prayer:</hi> thus the <hi>Publican</hi> ſtood afarr off and <hi>would not ſo much as lift up his eyes to heaven:</hi> as being unworthy<note place="margin">Luk. 18. 13.</note> to looke up to the throne of that great King, whoſe Lawes he had ſo often broken: even in his very addreſſes to God, when his broken heart (<hi>labouring and panting for the life of grace,</hi>) gaſps after nothing more, than to enjoy him in a cloſe &amp; choiſe communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;<note place="margin">Luk. 5. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo Job 7. 16. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, out of the ſenſe of Gods Majeſty and his miſery.</note> he is ready to cry out with <hi>Peter depart from me, for I am a ſinfull man, O Lord.</hi> When he thirſt's after nothing more than that God would draw near to him, in his drawing near to God, yet the ſenſe of his own vileneſs puts ſuch a check upon his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that he is ready to ſay, <hi>depart from me,</hi> when he is moſt ardently deſirous of his preſence. Lord I ſhall poiſon thee, wound thee, murder thee, in thy moſt ſaving meanes and mercies, I have ſuch a venomed contagious ſoule; therefore I muſt ſay, though I hope thou wilt not doe ſo; <hi>depart from me O Lord, for I am a ſinfull man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. When he compares himſelf with others, he bewails himſelf as worſe than any; nay worſe<note place="margin">Me tanquam ſigniferum pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teor. <hi>Clarius.</hi>
               </note> than the worſt of ſinners: ſo ſaid S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul 1 Tim. 1. 15. Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners, of whome I am chief.</hi> I know that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Grotius,</hi> and ſome others of great name (whoſe judgment I muſt beg pardon, if I cannot cloſe with in this) will have this humble confeſſion of the great Apoſtle to be nothing but an exceſs of modeſty, he knew (ſay they) there were ten thouſand worſe than he; but in pure modeſty
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115941:14"/> makes himſelf worſe than all: but we muſt becare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull we doe not make the Apoſtle to deliver lies; he did not uſe to complement with God or the world: and therefore (doubtleſs) the ſenſe of his own vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs made him ſpeake ſo of himſelf. It is a true rule that a broken heart will be vile in its own eyes: and as true it is that he that is higheſt in Gods eye is alwayes loweſt in his own eye.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> But how can this be made good that one of the greateſt Saints ſhould think himſelf one of the greateſt ſinners? is <hi>Paul</hi> turnd <hi>Saul</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> It may be made good upon a fourfold acount.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the kind of his ſin, it was a ſin of the firſt magnitude, a ſin of malice, the worſt of ſins, a devil-ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the end as well as the kind of his ſin: for his end in blaſpheming the goſpell, was only to eſtabliſh the righteouſneſs of the Law, which being a ſin ſo diametrically oppoſite to Chriſt, made him a greater ſinner then all the harlots and <hi>Publicans</hi> in the world.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtle compares himſelf only with the worſt of ſinners that were ſaved in his time, becauſe thoſe meanes prevailed for their converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that did not for his. <hi>Publicans</hi> and harlots were converted by the preaching of the Goſpel, nay even thoſe that crucified Chriſt: but if the Lord himſelf from heaven had not appeared to him, and in a moſt miraculous manner ſpoken to him himſelf, dazeled him into light, and blinded
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115941:15"/> him into ſight, and frighted him into obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, it is but too probable he had died in his ſin.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Duo cum faciunt idem, non eſt idem.</hi> One may commit the very ſame ſin another does, and yet there may be more malice and pollution in the one than in the other, as being heightened by many aggravating circumſtances, as committing the ſin againſt more light and ſtronger covictions, with a ſtronger bent of the will, and earneſtneſs and eagerneſſe of affections: and St. <hi>Paul</hi> here judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es how much of his ſpirit went out in his ſin. Surely no mans ſoul was ever drawn out with a more mad zeal to perſecute Chriſt, than his was: So that lay all together, and it will leſſen the wonder that he ſhould judge himſelf the chiefeſt of ſinners that Chriſt came to ſave, and he meanes no other; though I am not convinced but that a great Saint may ſay, he is as great a ſinner as any of the damned in hell, and I could make it good had I time, or were there need. But I will ſay it is very proper and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable to a broken heart to think ſo; for he cannot be thought to think too low of himſelf, that thinks himſelf nothing. And that is the</p>
            <p n="7">7. Broken ſigh, that in any thing, in every thing, the broken heart thinks himſelf loſt and nothing without Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And he may be ſaid to own himſelf nothing in four reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of his own righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In reſpect of his own pains and parts.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115941:15"/>3. In reſpect of his own aims and ends.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In reſpect of his own comforts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The broken heart is nothing in reſpect of his own righteouſneſs. He dares not ſtand up in his own juſtification, and plead his innocence before<note place="margin">Iſa. 64. 6.</note> the Tribunall of God; but rather falls down upon his face, acknowledging with the Prophet, that he is <hi>an unclean thing, and all his righteouſneſſes filthy raggs:</hi> all his righteouſneſſes: his pretty formalities of, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to holineſs: his pluralityes of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are but raggs, tattered and torn things that will not cover his nakedneſs, and filthy raggs, ſuch as defile rather than adorn him; with the <hi>Leper</hi> he lays his hand upon his mouth, and his<note place="margin">Lev. 13. 45.</note> mouth in the duſt, cries, <hi>Unclean, unclean.</hi> This low poſture you find the great Apoſtle in, <hi>Phil. 3. 9. That I may be found in Chriſt, not having mine own righteouſneſs.</hi> The whole ninth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Job</hi> is full of this holy emptineſs, and humble diſowning his own righteouſneſs: <hi>How ſhall I be juſt with God? I cannot anſwer one of a thouſand: If I justifie my ſelf, mine own mouth ſhall condemn me: If I ſay I am perfect, it ſhall alſo prove me perverſe: And I know thou wilt not hold me innocent.</hi> All which being ſummed up, amounts but to <hi>Davids</hi> totall, in that confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he makes, <hi>Pſal. 143. 2. Enter not into Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thy ſervant O Lord, for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified.</hi> Nay there is a thread of this renouncing and diſclaiming our own righteouſneſs, runs quite through the whole web
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115941:16"/> of Scripture, which ſhall ſuperſede any farther proofs: only take notice, that here is the great ſtick of an unbroken heart, you ſhall diſcover his ignorance and infidelity in this point mainly, that he is alwayes hammering at and fixi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g upon his own righteouſneſs, ſomething in himſelf. This is the language of ordinary people, their good prayers, and their good works, what they have done, and what they will do: Or if they be not altogether ſo groſs, they will yet mingle the righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt with their own: They will not take all to themſelves, nor yet give all to Chriſt; but part ſtakes with him, <hi>Nec meum, nec tuum, ſed dividatur,</hi> nor mine, nor<note place="margin">1 King. 3. 25.</note> thine, but let it be divided; like <hi>Salomons</hi> har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, and it was a whores trick, and it is the trick of the great whore at this day. But take notice, it was the mother of the dead childe that would have the living childe divided;——at leaſt if they may not ſhare and club with Chriſt, they will have Chriſt in a way of their own: not to make an Idol of Chriſt, O have a care of that: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he that truly findes he is any thing in Chriſt, will as truly finde he is nothing in himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt. It is the character of a Chriſtian (which I am ſure a man can never be till his heart be broken) that he is nothing, a very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, a thing that is not: His very being is not to be at all; this ſame miracle of men, and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery to men a Saint, is not a man, nay is not at all. See how the Apoſtle cleares this truth, 1 <hi>Cor. 1. 27, 28. God hath choſen the fooliſh things,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115941:16"/> and the weak things, and the baſe things,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the things that are not, to bring to nought the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homines nibili</hi> Eraſm. <hi>in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>things that are.</hi> Certainly theſe things that are not, are the Saints, that is, that are not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but that being they have, is in another, not only naturally, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> quotes the Poet, <hi>Act. 17. 28. In whom we live, move, and have our being;</hi> but that ſupernaturall being of a Chriſtian is wholly from and in Chriſt: From him they have their <hi>nature,</hi> as well as <hi>name,</hi> and therefore called <hi>Partakers of the divine nature,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 4. So<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſignificat cauſam prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam, ut</hi> Rom. 11. 36. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Theoph.</hi> Eraſ. Gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 1 <hi>Cor. 1. 30. But of him are ye in Chriſt Jeſus, that ye are at all, it is not at all of your ſelves, but of him, that is Chriſt: By the grace of God I am what I am,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 10. <hi>Otherwiſe I am not.</hi> Gal. 2. 20. <hi>I live, yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me.</hi> You have this ſpirituall man (that is a heart broken from the world, and dead to it) painted to the life, by the Pencill of the Spirit in that <hi>Phaenix</hi> of the old world, <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>och, Gen. 5. 24. Enoch walked with God, and was not, for God took him.</hi> I am not ignorant that St. <hi>Paul</hi> takes this in the literall ſenſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 5. but I hope I may faſten a ſpirituall ſenſe upon it; it may have one mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the letter, and another in the ſpirit: Not that I mean it in that groſs (yet thin, ſleight) way, ſome of our late Allegoriſts have fancied it, (notionall Divines) that have ſpun Religion into ſo fine a thread, it will not hold the wearing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in practice, ſleight and light Cob-web-Laun-Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which as it hath much of the art of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſo it hath not a little of the Venome. For
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115941:17"/> the former part of it, that <hi>Enoch walked with God,</hi> is wholly ſpirituall; that is, as the Apoſtle elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where interprets himſelf, He <hi>walked not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit;</hi> and why may not the<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 1. <hi>Cum</hi> Jove <hi>vivere</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſ. <hi>Aſſumptum</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ait</hi> Baſil. Sel. <hi>ſic alti de Elijah.</hi>
               </note> other part be ſo too? <hi>He was not, for God took him;</hi> that is, he was not <hi>in himſelf,</hi> but God took <hi>him to himſelf</hi> in a ſenſe of <hi>grace,</hi> as well as <hi>glory.</hi> He was not, or he was nothing, but what he was he was in Chriſt: in the Hebrew it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and he was not he,</hi> very patt to the phraſe of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal. 2. 20. I live, yet not I, but Chriſt lives in me.</hi> I and not I: <hi>Ego non ſum ego,</hi> I am not I, I am nothing in or of my ſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A broken heart is broken not only all to pieces, but even thoſe pieces annihilated and made nothing, at leaſt to his own eye, in reſpect of his own pains and parts, abilityes, and endeavours. He ſees himſelf ſuch a barren ſoil, that all the manuring and husbandry of art and nature will make no tilth of him, bring nothing out of him without Chriſt, as Chriſt ſaies, <hi>John 15. 5. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me ye can do nothing.</hi> Such a man hath an excellent wit, a ſtupendious memory, a moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive judgement; but O if he have nothing of Chriſt, all theſe excellencies are but flowers and ribbands upon a dead Corpſe, <hi>ut majore cum pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pâ deſcendat ad inferos,</hi> that he may go to hell in more ſtate. Chriſt is the ſtandard of every mans value: A man is worth juſt as much and no more,<note place="margin">Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 15. 5.</note> as he hath of Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>Without me ye can do nothing, without me ye are nothing.</hi> A broken heart
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115941:17"/> is ſenſible that he wants Chriſt, not only for the great work of ſalvation, but for every particular leſſer act of a Chriſtian. He cannot hear a Sermon without Chriſt; he cannot read a Chapter without Chriſt; he cannot lift up a prayer without Chriſt. The very expreſſion of lifting up a prayer ſpeakes weight, and it is ſuch a weight, as the lifting up our hands cannot lift up alone: And therefore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſayes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">I appeal to the learned whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this may not be the ſenſe of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Jam. 5. 16.</note> 
               <hi>the Spirit helpeth our infirmities,</hi> but in the Original propriety; the Spirit joyns as it were a ſhoulder to ours to help to lift up this Heave-offering of prayer. O the deadneſs of duties, when men throw themſelves only upon the wings of their own abilities! How are their mouths ſtopped many times in the middle of a duty? How narrow, how ſhort do they fall in prayer? What dead Sacrifices do they offer to the living God? as <hi>Mary</hi> ſaid to Chriſt, <hi>Lord if thou hadſt been here my Brother had not died,</hi> Joh. 11. 21. So certainly the reaſon why we offer ſuch carkaſſes of duties, is becauſe the Lord is not there. This is that which makes our wheeles move ſo heavily in any ſervices, becauſe the Spirit is not in<note place="margin">Ezek. 1. 20.</note> the wheels; that <hi>good Spirit that raiſed Jeſus Chriſt from the dead,</hi> doth not raiſe us from dead works, to ſerving the <hi>living God</hi> in a living way.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A broken heart thinks himſelf nothing in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his own aims and ends. He is clearly <hi>raſa Tabula,</hi> white Paper not ſcribled, and blurred, and blotted with the buſineſs and projects of the world; he is wholly reſolved into his Maſters dictates; he bids do and he doth it. He hath no plots but how
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115941:18"/> he may beſt ſerve Chriſt, and makes all other ends truckle under that of ſerving God in his generation. All other people but thoſe whoſe hearts God hath ſweetly and ſavingly broken, have ends of their own, and ſerve themſelves upon God, even in their pretenſes of ſerving him. <hi>Jehu</hi> will have all the world believe he doth Gods work in deſtroying the houſe of <hi>Ahab;</hi> and that it may be taken notice of,<note place="margin">2 King. 10. 16</note> he blowes a Trumpet before it, <hi>Come and ſee my zeal for the Lord;</hi> but all was but to ſerve his own ambitious ends: and therefore when God comes to reckon with him, and pay him his wages, he calls it murther, and revenges bloud with bloud, <hi>Hoſ. 1. 4. I will avenge the bloud of Jezreel upon the houſe of Jehu.</hi> The <hi>Phariſees</hi> did Gods work indeed, and it was good work, to pray, and to give almes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but they did one Chair for their Maſter, and two for themſelves; they ſerved their own baſe pride and covetouſneſs to be ſeen of men, and to devour wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows houſes: And it is worth our obſervation, how God proportions their <hi>wages</hi> to their <hi>works,</hi> they ſerve him with <hi>works that are outwardly duties and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ſins;</hi> and he payes them with <hi>wages that are outwardly rewards, but judgements within: They have</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 6. 2.</note> 
               <hi>their reward</hi> ſaith Chriſt; but what is that? They <hi>pretended</hi> my praiſe, but <hi>intended</hi> their own praiſe, and they have it; they have the <hi>honour of man,</hi> but ſhall never have <hi>any of the glory of God.</hi> I do not go about to catechize you in this point. I am much taken off from enquiring into the ends why you came hither, with the joy to ſee you here: But yet let me tell you, it were very good if you did ask your ſelves
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115941:18"/> that Queſtion which God did <hi>Eliah, What doſt thou here Eliah?</hi> Sure I am upon ſuch an enquiry, a<note place="margin">2 Kings 9 9. Pſal. 39. 8.</note> broken heart would return an Anſwer to this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion by another Queſtion, Lord what are my ends? And give that Queſtion <hi>Davids</hi> Anſwer, <hi>And now what is my hope, truly my hope is even in thee?</hi> So are my ends only in thee; thou art my <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga:</hi> my <hi>terminus à quo,</hi> and my <hi>terminus ad quem;</hi> my beginning, my end, and my all: Lord what are the ends of my faith, and prayers, and hearing, and works of mercy, are they not to honour thee my dear Redeemer! Curſe them, curſe them, blaſt them Lord, if they ſavour of any intereſt but that of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. My own heart is a witneſs to me, and thou art a witneſs to my heart, that I come not with <hi>Herod</hi> for curioſity, or with the people for loaves, but for a dear affection, which draws me to thee with a magnetick energy. <hi>Thy love is</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>better then wine,</hi> Cant. 5. 1. And as the Spouſe there goes on <hi>verſ. 2. Becauſe of the ſavour of thy good oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>therefore do the Virgins love thee. Draw me and I will run after thee.</hi> That ointment, that oil of gladneſs which thou art annointed withall above thy fellows, and that which thou doſt annoint thy fellows withall, that is, thoſe that be in fellowſhip and communion with thee, it is that that draws me, and I muſt run after thee. Alas! I am a dull hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy piece of iron, I have no motion of mine own, but thou art my loadſtone, and my loadſtar: I am but a poor inconſiderable Straw, good for nothing but the fire, but thou art the lovely Jett, that forceſt me to leap up to thee, as the Apoſtle ſayes, <hi>The love of</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 14.</note>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115941:19"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt conſtrains me,</hi> for of my ſelf I am nothing, and good for nothing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A broken heart is nothing, in reſpect of his own Comforts and Contentments: he can take comfort in nothing, till he ſees God reach out the mercy to him: he dares not be his own Carver to ſnatch at any thing, but waiſes with patience and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, till his Father give it him: ſo that he may ſay of all his enjoyments, as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid of his Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon but more truely, <hi>the Lord thy God brought it to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 27. 20. Gen. 2. 22.</note> 
               <hi>me:</hi> he owns no comfort in Wife or Children, health or wealth, or any of thoſe things that we are apt to call goods, and think mercies, but as he ſees they are from God: <hi>As Adam took Eve when God brought her to him: Theſe are the Children which the Lord hath given thy Servant,</hi> Gen. 33. O this is the mercy of a mercy, the comfort of a comfort, the Crowne of a broken heart in his ſaddeſt condition; this is that which raiſes, refreſhes, raviſhes his ſoul when he can ſee God in a mercy: this is that <hi>Elixar</hi> of a broken heart, turns all to Gold, <hi>Pſal. 37. 16. A little that a righteous man hath, is better than the riches of many wicked.</hi> Many wicked, as if he had ſaid, all the riches of the wealthy wicked ones in the world, will not amount to ſuch a Summe, nor riſe to ſuch an Income of comfort, nor ſwell to ſo vaſt a Revenue of contentment, as thoſe little pittances that the Father is pleaſed to give with his own hands to his own Children. When God ſhall convey a bleſſing to a man through the <hi>Covenant of grace,</hi> when it flowes in to him through <hi>Prayers and Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> theſe are the <hi>eldeſt Sonnes of mercy that are
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115941:19"/> the heires of the Promiſes:</hi> Oh there is a hidden Manna in thoſe mercies that are <hi>reached out by the hand of Promiſe, reached at by the hand of faith,</hi> given by the hand of Providence, and taken by the hand of Prayer. <hi>All my ſprings are in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> ſayes <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 87. <hi>ult.</hi> All ſprings, there is their U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſality: my ſprings, there's their Propriety; in thee, there is their Eternity. All my ſprings, my ſprings of <hi>Axa,</hi> my upper ſprings, and my lower ſprings, my ſprings of grace, my ſprings of Peace here: my ſprings of joy, my ſprings of glory above, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> all thoſe living foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of that great depth of Eternity: All my ſprings are in thee. Carnal hearts have their muddy ponds, and ſtinking puddles, out of which they think they can fetch waters of comfort; but, alas, when they taſte them, they prove but waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> bitter waters, they come from, and flow into the dead Sea, there are ſnares in them, <hi>there is death in the Pot:</hi> at beſt, <hi>they are but broken Ciſterns</hi> (as God cals<note place="margin">Jer. 7. 11.</note> them) <hi>that will hold no water;</hi> whereas, this bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken<note place="margin">Jer. 2. 13.</note> Ciſtern of Gods making, a broken heart may freely fill himſelf with that, which alone can fill, <hi>the fountain of living waters.</hi> For God as he is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercies, ſo he is the God of all comforts, who only can give comforts as a God, that is, ſuch<note place="margin">1 Cor 1. 3.</note> comforts as man cannot give, and ſuch comforts as man cannot take away. All are miſerable comforts and comforters, (as <hi>Job</hi> ſaies) that are dig'd out of the<note place="margin">Job 16. 2.</note> Creature: <hi>Conſolatiunculae Creaturulae,</hi> as <hi>Luther</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to diminutive it. A broken heart would taſte a great deal of ſweetneſs in that one delicious promiſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115941:20"/> 
               <hi>that flows with milk and hony, wine and oyle, marrow and fatneſs,</hi> Eſay 58. 11 <hi>And the Lord ſhall guide thee continually, and ſatisfie thy ſoul in drought</hi> (it is in droughts in the Original, in the hotteſt hardeſt ſeaſon) <hi>and make fat thy bones, and thou ſhalt be like a watred Garden, and like a ſpring of water, whoſe waters faile not,</hi> Hebr. <hi>whoſe waters lye not, or deceive not.</hi> O all theſe lower ſprings are ſuch, not filling and yet failing, not laſting and yet lying, deceiving as well as decaying waters. All the life of the toyling worldling (in the midſt of his pleaſing dreams and gay hopes that flatter him with golden Indies as the return of his drudgery) is (if <hi>really</hi> and <hi>rationally,</hi> as well as <hi>religiouſly conſidered,</hi>) but like the ſad trade of the poore <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to go up and down to ſeek ſtraw, to take a great deal of pains to make up their Bundle, and when they have it, it is but a bundle, and that bundle is but ſtraw, and that ſtraw but to make Brick, to put an edge upon their affliction, and with a great deal of wit and labour to adde new weights to that which is but too heavy without it. Methinks the buſineſſe of the world is moſt meltingly emblemd in that paſſionate expreſſion of the poor Widow to the Prophet. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 17. 12.</note> 
               <hi>I am gathering two sticks, that I may go in and dreſs a little Cake for me and my ſon, that we may eat it and dye:</hi> take a great deal of pains, to take a little pleaſure, and dye: and many times when a man hath made up his bundle, and reſolves to ſit down and warm himſelf and ſay <hi>Aha,</hi> (as the Prophet<note place="margin">Eſa. 44 16.</note> moſt rhetorically humors it) when a man thinks to enjoy the ſweet of his labours, to make his gold
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115941:20"/> fuſive and malleable, run it and beat it out into the varied delights of his ownfancy, when he is going to ſet fire to his bundle, and pleaſes himſelf with the chearing project of pleaſing himſelf and his friends<note place="margin">Acts 28. 3.</note> with its warmth. How often doth it prove like St. <hi>Pauls</hi> bundle of ſticks? There comes a viper out of it, ſome ſting, ſome venome, ſome vexation to poiſon and ſowr his contentments. What do they do that burden their bodies, their brains, their ſouls too, to loade themſelves with thick clay (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet<note place="margin">Hab. 2. 6.</note> elegantly) but like men preſſed to death, cry more weight ſtill? We run here and there like the Prophets vagrant, and grudge if we be not ſatisfied, but we are not ſatisfied for all our grudging: We<note place="margin">Pſalm 59. 15.</note> knock at the doore of every Creature, but one ſayes 'tis not in me, and the other ſay it is not in me: there is nothing within to entertain us and bid us wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come:<note place="margin">Job 28. 14.</note> Riches, Relations, Learning, Liberty, have nothing in them, any further than we can ſee God in them: indeed, to ſee God in any thing though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſtaires is a <hi>beatifical viſion,</hi> and makes even a <hi>Hell a Heaven:</hi> which makes me often think that ſpeech of <hi>Luther</hi> not ſo wilde, as ſome would have it, <hi>Mallem eſſe in Inferno cum Chriſto, quàm in cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſine Chriſto.</hi> I had rather be in Hell with Chriſt, than in Heaven without him: it is the King that makes the Court. This is Sugar to the moſt bitter Cup of Affliction. A man may make a meal of ſowr herbs with contentment, when he ſees God in it as a Paſſeover, when the lintels and doore-poſts<note place="margin">Exod 12. 7.</note> are ſprinkled with the blood of the Lamb, when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very bit he eat sis dipped in the blood of Jeſus Chriſt.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115941:21"/> It is a rare Cordiall to a fainting ſpirit, when he can ſee God in his diſtreſſes, though but as the <hi>Sun in April</hi> through a <hi>ſhowr</hi> of <hi>teares.</hi> Nay S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Stephen</hi> had joy in his death when he ſaw God and Chriſt at<note place="margin">Acts 7. 55, 56. 58.</note> his right hand, though through a <hi>ſhowr</hi> of <hi>ſtones.</hi> There is more in that Text of <hi>David</hi> then is ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily diſcovered, <hi>Pſal. 4. 7. Lord lift up the light of thy countenance upon me: Thou haſt put gladneſs in my hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, more then in the time that their corn and wine encreaſed,</hi> that is, not only more then theſe poor empty creatures of corn and wine can give; or more then their corn and wine, that is, more then they can give them whoſe they are, (though certainly they are the moſt refreſhing creatures, and they have the higheſt guſt of their refreſhments whoſe they are, that are their proprieters) not only <hi>more then corn and wine,</hi> and <hi>their corn and wine,</hi> but <hi>more then in the time of their corn and wine,</hi> that is, the Harveſt and the Vintage, the merrieſt ſeaſons of all the year. Thus <hi>David</hi> preferres his joy he had in God, as he did <hi>Jeruſalem, Pſal. 137. 6. Above my chief joy,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Above the head of my joy. This ſight of God in any condition is the top and pinacle of all joy, for this <hi>ſupplyes what a man has not, and ſweetens what he has.</hi> This was that which ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin">Gen. 28. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Jacobs</hi> dream, and ſoftned his hard pillow, that beſides <hi>the Angels he ſaw aſcending and deſcending upon his ladder, the Lord God ſtood above.</hi> Thus have I gathered up the fragments of the firſt piece the heart is broken into, in ſhewing you all thoſe low thoughts it has of it ſelf.</p>
            <p>It is now high time to come to the</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115941:21"/>
            <p>2. His high thoughts of God. This piece of a broken heart is ſo great that it may be broken into many more; but I will only name five, and I will little more then only name them. 1. Submiſſion to the will of God. 2. Sorrow for ſinning againſt the will of God. 3. Shame, as the proper iſſue of that ſorrow. 4. Fear that he may ſin againſt him again. 5. Prayer that he may not.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Submiſſion to the will of God. The broken heart lyes at the foot of Gods will, to do, to be any thing, nothing. A broken heart is a heart after Gods heart, that is, is ready to fullfill all Gods will, as God characters his ſervant <hi>David,</hi> Act. 13. 22. <hi>A man after mine own heart, that ſhall fullfill all my will;</hi> it is <hi>wills</hi> in the Original, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>all my wills.</hi> A broken heart is a heart broken to, (as well as by) Gods hands, to do what he will, to ſuffer what he will. Like his great pattern and principle of obedience Jeſus Chriſt, he firſt ſacrifices his will, and then all he has and is to the will of God; <hi>not as I will, but as thou wilt.</hi> He cryes, <hi>The will of the Lord be done, though I be undone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. He does what God will have him do, though he dye for it. It is not neceſſary that I ſhould live, ſayes he, but it is neceſſary that God ſhould be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and therefore he willingly takes the yoke of Chriſt upon him. Thy will is my ſanctification, ſayes the broken heart, and that is it I would will too; that is it I would be at rather then my life, a life of grace rather then a life of nature; I would fain be holy, and live up to the ſtandard of thy Word; I ſee a great deal of beauty in holineſs, and though there be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115941:22"/> a great deal of <hi>weakneſs</hi> in me as to the <hi>attaining</hi> of it, yet there is a great deal of <hi>willingneſs</hi> in me as to the <hi>embracing</hi> it. <hi>Thy people ſhall be willing in the day of thy power,</hi> Pſal. 110. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Populus volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> ſayes <hi>Vatablus;</hi> but why not <hi>Voluntates?</hi> they ſhall be all wills, for all thou wilt, as <hi>Pſal. 109. 4. But I give my ſelf unto prayer;</hi> it is <hi>Heb.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> But I am prayer, I am all prayer for them, I only or alwayes pray for them, that only or alwayes prey upon me. So for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Thy people are all wills, that is, all reſolved into thy will, or reſolved into all thy wills, they are delivered up to the will of God. So <hi>Rom. 6. 17. Ye have received from the heart,</hi> the broken heart, <hi>that form of doctrine which was delivered to you,</hi> or rather to which ye were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>their hard hearts were melted into the will of God, for this is in the day of thy power,</hi> that is, when thou haſt powerfully broken their hearts. This poſture you ſee St <hi>Paul</hi> in, <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 6, When the Lord had unhorſed him, and he lay upon the earth trembling, aſtoniſhed, and blind, he cryes<note place="margin">Acts 9. 6.</note> out, <hi>Lord, what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> As <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſayes, <hi>Adhaeret pavimento anima mea,</hi> Pſal. 119. So his ſoul cleaved to the duſt, as well as his body; he lay groveling in the duſt of his own broken heart, as well as that of the earth; his heart was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly broken from his own will, wholly into the will of God; he lyes at the foot of Gods will for orders, and when he gives the word, he obeys. A bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart is like the <hi>Centurions</hi> ſervant, when his Maſter ſayes, <hi>goe, he goes; and come, he comes; do this, and he does it.</hi> This is exampled in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115941:22"/> if God call him out of his native Countrey, and his Fathers houſe, nay out of his own Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and bid him ſacrifice the name and nature of a Father, in ſacrificing his ſon, his only ſon, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes not, but <hi>ſtat pro ratione voluntas.</hi> His Maſters will is his law; and therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Eſa. 41. 2. He raiſed up the righteous man from the Eaſt, called him to his foot.</hi> That which is <hi>Heb.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> we tranſlate <hi>the righteous man;</hi> and juſtly, becauſe meant of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as the <hi>Caldee Paraphraſe</hi> cleares it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Abraham</hi> the choiſe and famous man for righteouſneſs. And it alludes to that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Deut. 33. 3. <hi>All his Saints are in thy hand, and they ſit down at thy feet, every one ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of thy words</hi> (that is) are at thy feet in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of ſervants and ſcholars, that heare, to learn, and obey: ſo obedient <hi>Abraham</hi> follows his maſter ſtep by ſtep whereſoever he goes, as the Poet, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The broken heart lyes at the foote of Gods will, to ſuffer as well as to doe, what he will: he can <hi>dy</hi> for, as well as <hi>doe,</hi> and <hi>live</hi> to the will of God whether he pleaſe to delay or deny the good he has not, or take away the good he has: when a mans heart is broken from the world, he is not ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous for any of the concernes of the world. <hi>I am cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to the world and the world to me</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul.</hi> And doe you thinke a man that is crucified or broken upon the wheele, or rack, will care much, what his Cloathes, or diet, or room is. The broken heart is at a point for all outward things, he is content with <hi>any thing,</hi> becauſe he is <hi>nothing. I have larned</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115941:23"/> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul in whatſoever eſtate I am, therewith to be content: I know how to be abaſed, and how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound,</hi> Phil. 4. 11. <hi>I have quieted my ſelf as a child that is weaned from his mother, my ſoul is even as a weaned child,</hi> Pſal. 131. 3. <hi>I do not lament for the teates, for the pleaſant fields, or fruitfull vines,</hi> Eſa. 32. 12. I was a froward child indeed, and cryed for all the fine things I ſaw; but now I am broken from all theſe things, weaned from the gay nothings that pleaſe the children of the world. I am brought up by hand; what my dear Father gives me, that I take thankfully. I eat and am ſatisfied, and praiſe the Name of the Lord. The great heart-breaking of the men of the world is, that they have not ſo great a ſhare in the world as others; <hi>Vicinumque pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus grandius uber habet.</hi> Whereas the truly bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken-hearted regards not what the world is to him, or he is in the world. O ſayes the broken heart, the very <hi>brokenneſs of my heart makes my heart whole!</hi> 'Tis true I am very poor, my houſe poor, my fare poor, my all is poor; but this doth not break my heart, becauſe my heart is broke for better things. My heart is broken by God, and for God; the clefts of my broken heart, <hi>hiatus cordis,</hi> the deſires of my heart are gaping after him. Though I be poor, I court not the God of riches, but I gaſp after the riches of God. I am rich even in my poverty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have a rich God, and if he give me no more, yet that I have is more then <hi>he owes me of debt,</hi> and more then I can pay him for in <hi>duty.</hi> When pride is never contented, his houſe, his cloathes, his diet are never good enough, becauſe his heart is not bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115941:23"/> He that is full of his own brokenneſs, is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the worlds fulneſs, like his Maſter Chriſt, <hi>exinanivit ſeipſum;</hi> he is full of nothing but his own emptineſs, and therefore ſees nothing but <hi>emptineſs</hi> in the <hi>worlds fulneſs.</hi> He ſees all is vanity, and that truly the whole world is but a great nothing; theſe outward things are all but phantaſms, they have no reall being in themſelves, but are only what we creat them in our fancyes: beſides meate and drinke and clothes, all the reſt is meerly opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As the Preacher ſayes <hi>Eccl. 5. 11. when goods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, they are increaſed that eat them: and what good is there to the owners thereof, ſaving the behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them with their eyes?</hi> Loaden diſhes, ſwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bowles, gay clothes, great houſes, vaſt rents numerous Retinue, are nothing but what the worlds<note place="margin">Gen 33. 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> flattery, and our own fancy creates them; the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God calls them no more: for when King <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa, Bernice,</hi> and <hi>Feſtus</hi> came in great ſtate to hear St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Act. 25. 23. <hi>When Agrippa was come and Bernice with great pomp;</hi> it is in the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with a great deal of fancy: ſo true is that <hi>Arabick</hi> Proverb, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the world is not in the <hi>muches,</hi> but in the <hi>enoughs. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna multis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imium dedit, nulli ſatis:</hi> Many think they have never enough, though they have never ſo much. And therefore it is very obſervable how thoſe two Brothers <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> differ in their expreſſions in the <hi>Heb.</hi> when they ſeem to paſs the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement in our Tranſlation. <hi>Eſau</hi> refuſes <hi>Jacobs</hi> preſent, <hi>becauſe</hi> ſayes he, <hi>I have enough my Brother;</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> preſſes it upon the ſame termes, <hi>Take I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115941:24"/> pray thee my bleſſing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>becauſe I have enough:</hi> But <hi>Eſau</hi> ſayes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>I have much,</hi> but <hi>Jacobs</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I have all. Eſau</hi> had <hi>much</hi> becauſe he had <hi>a great deal,;</hi> but <hi>Jacob</hi> had <hi>all</hi> becauſe he had <hi>enough;</hi> which <hi>all</hi> had not been <hi>enough</hi> neither, but that <hi>God</hi> was his <hi>all,</hi> and that <hi>all</hi> makes not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>much,</hi> but <hi>enough</hi> of <hi>nothing;</hi> and if God will give him nothing, or take away that little,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 3. 18. 2 Sam. 15. 26. Eſa. 3. Job 1. 21.</note> more than nothing, he has given him, as he gave all, ſo if he take away al from him; <hi>It is the Lord, ſayes</hi> Eli. <hi>It is the Lord, ſayes</hi> David, <hi>let him doe what ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good unto him. God forbid that ſhould ſeem ill to me that ſeems good to God Good is the word of the Lord, ſaies</hi> Hezekiah; <hi>The Lord gives and the Lord takes away, ſayes</hi> Job, <hi>bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> He gives thanks when God takes, as well as gives, when the Lord comes with a <hi>voiding knife</hi> and <hi>takes away his meate,</hi> as well a when he <hi>layes his cloth,</hi> and <hi>furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es his table,</hi> becauſe his <hi>Grace</hi> is in his <hi>meale.</hi> Thus you have ſeene the firſt high thoughts of God the <hi>Heart is broken into,</hi> expreſſed in his humble ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the will of God, in being willing to doe and and ſuffer his will.</p>
            <p>There remain four other perticulars in which a broken heart ſpeaks loudly his high thoughts of God, as 1 Sorrow for ſinning againſt him. 2 Shame as well as ſorrow. 3 Feare leaſt he may ſin again. And 4 Prayer that he may not. But this though a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of our frait to lighten our veſſel and ſhorten our voyage, I was content ſhould be ſwallowed in the quick ſands of the hourglaſſe; and I will not weigh them up again for your eys that were
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115941:24"/> drowned to your eares: but rather tack about to the next point, which is the,</p>
            <p n="2">2 Thing: How a man may judg whether his heart were ever throughly broken and truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite: and I ſhall give you Four ſhort Rules for this.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Philoſophers ſay <hi>Durum non cedit, &amp; durum non ſentit.</hi> Hard things yeild not, feell not; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hardneſſe of heart and contempt of Gods word and commandment are linked together as a chaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bullet, to be prayed againſt in that excellent peice of our Leiturgy the Letany. I ſhall therefore lay it down as a cleare ſymptome of a broken heart, when it is ſenſible of its own hardneſs: when it ſighs and weepes, and bleeds over it, and prayes againſt it,<note place="margin">Ut amplius no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> indureſcat cor noſtrum, ſed ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat tibi, <hi>&amp;c. Forer.</hi>
               </note> as they, <hi>Eſ. 63. 17, O Lord why haſt thou made us to erre from thy ways and hardened our hearts from thy feare? return for thy ſervants ſake.</hi> O ther's nothing ſpeaks a broken heart more emphatically, than a ſenſe of, and ſorrow for its own hardneſs; as Divines ſay of the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, that when a man is afraid he has committed it, and grieves for it, it is a ſigne he has not committed it; ſo when a man complaines of a hard heart it is a bleſſed ſymptome his heart is not hard. St <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> has a paſſage to this purpoſe, of a friend of his that came crying and bellowing to him beſeeching him to helpe to break his hard heart. O ſayes the good Father the worke is done; thou couldeſt never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have thy heart broken if it were not broken already. Therefore if you wold know whether your heart be broken, aske your ſelves this queſtion, whether you deſire to have it broken, from a ſenſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115941:25"/> of, and ſorrow for, its hardneſſe. Sorrow is the great heart breaker under God whoſe hammer it is to breake this ſtone, and therefore <hi>ſorrow</hi> that thy <hi>heart is not broken</hi> is a ſigne thy heart is broken: it is a ſigne that God has ſtruck the the Rock when the water guſhes out: the weeping of the marble is a degree of ſoftening, at the leaſt a propheſy of and a preparation to its crumbleing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Catechiſe your ſoul with this Interrogatory, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you prize a broken heart or no? He that never truly valued a broken heart, never deſired a broken heart, and he that never deſired a broken heart, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had a broken heart. There are two ſorts of hearts that God chiefly prizes, the <hi>upright heart,</hi> and the <hi>contrite heart,</hi> and theſe are inſeparable, for that heart can never be upright, that never was contrite: and therefore St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayes, <hi>I am daily a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Queſtion to my ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He that hath a broken heart, his heart hath<note place="margin">Joel 2. 12. Jer. 4. 3.</note> been active in, and to its own breaking. <hi>Rent your hearts and not your garments,</hi> do you rent them your ſelves. <hi>Plough up your fallow ground, and ſow not among thornes,</hi> do you your ſelves plough them up. You are not to ſtay in an idle expectation that God would break your hearts for you. The drunkard muſt not ſtay at his Cups till his Wine inflame him, ſquander away his precious houres, (which muſt one day be ſadly accounted for) diſhonour God, abuſe his mercies, and (perhaps) wretchedly guzle down his Childrens bread, and his Wives tears, and think that God ſhould pluck the Pot from his noſe, and drag him out by the ears, break the knot of good
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115941:25"/> fellows that ſo tyes him to his debaucheries, that he may break his heart whether he will or no. The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean perſon muſt not think that God ſhould come <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſnatch him from his <hi>Dalilahs</hi> lap to <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, and ſay he ſtaies but till God will break his heart, but he muſt pray and grieve and ſtrive and avoid all occaſions, or elſe he doth like the<note place="margin">See this and more in Dr. <hi>Heyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng. Hiſt. Quinquart.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lantgrave</hi> of <hi>Turing,</hi> of whom <hi>Heiſtibachius</hi> tels us, that being warnd of his lewd and looſe life, and the ſadneſs of his condition, if he ſhould dye in his ſins, that he made this wretched anſwer: <hi>Si praede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatus ſum nulla peccata poterunt regnum Caelorum auferre, ſi praeſcitus, nulla opera mihi illud vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt auferre:</hi> if I be elected, no ſins can hinder me from Heaven, if I be reprobated no ſervices can help me to it: therefore you muſt be active in breaking your own hearts your own ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But how ſhall we do it? Alas we would do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all our hearts if we knew how.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> Why I will tell you: you muſt do it, by taking in all humbling and ſoftning and heart-breaking conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, <hi>viz.</hi> the hatefulneſs of ſin, the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſin, the deceitfulneſs of your own hearts, the dreadfulneſs of wrath, the goodneſs of God that leads to repentance, and the ſeverity of God, if thou repent not, <hi>But after thy hardneſſe and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>heart, treaſureſt up unto thy ſelf wrath againſt the day of wrath.</hi> Set the hammer of the word to this ſtone, and ſee if that cannot break it. Apply the Bloud of Chriſt warm by faith, and ſee if that cannot break this Adamant. Let the love of Chriſt break it, as we do flints upon a pillow. I know there is another way of breaking and melting the heart
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115941:26"/> which God often uſes, but it is commonly when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe will. But he that deſerves and deſires it, let him have it. They ſay indeed, that fire will make flints run. But ô it is a ſhame for us, that weare the name of Chriſt in ſuch large Phylacteries of a loud Profeſſion, ſhould be overgrown with ſuch a hardneſs, as not to be made fuſile and ductile, mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leable at leaſt, fit to take the impreſſion of Gods ſtamp and image, we have defaced, without ſo intenſe a heat as a fiery Furnace.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whoſoever's heart is broken, nothing will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie<note place="margin">Matth. 4.</note> him but pardoning mercy. Give him the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils offer to Chriſt, <hi>the world and all the glory of it.</hi> All the ſplendor and grandeur, the pomp, peace, plenty and pleaſure the whole world can afford in all outward Accommodations, are all empty Ciphers, inſignificant nothings to him, till he ſees God ſhine upon him in the face of Jeſus Chriſt. O nothing can binde up the wound of a broken heart, but a ſight of God reconciled in Jeſus Chriſt. God hath par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned me, Chriſt is mine, Heaven is mine: this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone will do the work, and nothing till this: of other mercies, till this, and without this he cries with <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, Suſpectam habeo hanc Dei indulgentiam,</hi> theſe are ſuſpicious mercies I will have none of them; and with St. <hi>Bernard, Miſericordiam hanc nolo Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine:</hi> and as the Tradition goes of <hi>Thomas Aquinas, Bene de me ſcripſiſti Thoma, quam ergo mercedem accipies? Nullam Domine praeter teipſam. Thomas</hi> thou haſt written well of me, what reward wilt thou have? None but thy ſelf Lord. Look upon a broken heart on his death-bed, when his body is breaking into duſt. <hi>O the end of that man is peace,</hi> ſee him<note place="margin">Pſalm 37. 37.</note>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115941:26"/> entring upon the confines of eternity, with what pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, with what peace, with what pleaſure, can he ſee the glory and beauty of the world melt and moulder away? he can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, relations, liberty nay life it ſelf ſlide from him with no more diſturbance, and with more comfort and contentment, than Paſſengers in a Boat upon the <hi>Thames,</hi> ſee the great City, and the fair houſes glide from them, when their buſineſs is at <hi>Whitehall</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the City and Court of the great King: His ſoul is landed in Heaven al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. It was rarely ſpoken by that old Souldier of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who having received his deaths wound in one of his many battles, when he was above 80. years old, and his friends coming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him to condole and comfort him againſt the fear of death, what ſaies he, have I lived above four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore years, and do you think I do not know how to die a quarter of an hour? he can die any day, every day,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 25. 31.</note> that dies daily: his heart will never be <hi>broken for leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the world at his death, whoſe heart hath bin broken in leaving the world in his life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I have nothing to do now, but only to give you two words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To quicken you to get your hearts broken, if they be not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To caution you that you be ſure they are broken.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That you would get your hearts broken if they be not: and that for two ſhort Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is from the Text, that this is the only ſacrifice that God will <hi>not deſpiſe,</hi> this he <hi>ownes and loves above all others,</hi> at leaſt, <hi>all others for and in this:</hi> All <hi>ſacrifices and ſervices</hi> without this, are but <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115941:27"/> ſacrifices, broken ſervices:</hi> A ſacrifice without a heart was a <hi>Prodigy,</hi> and without a broken heart is a <hi>Profanation:</hi> that which <hi>break<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> makes</hi> us: <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus opem tulit:</hi> our <hi>wounds blee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>am.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A broken and contrite heart gives you a key into Gods preſence-chamber; you have a Patent for it under Gods hand and ſeal: will you ſee the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? <hi>Eſay 57. 15. Thus ſaith the high and lofty one that inhabits eternity, whoſe name is holy: I dwell in the high and the holy place, with him alſo that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit, to revive the pir it of the humble, and to revive the ſpirit of the contrite ones:</hi> Here is oyle of Gladneſſe indeed, but it is a broken veſſel that muſt receive it, a broken and humble heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To caution, as well as quicken you, that you give not over the work till you be ſure your hearts are broken: I ſhall hint four Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe your hearts are deceitfull, and apt to put a cheate upon you, eſpecially in this duty, this irkſome duty, of ſearching your own hearts, to be ſatisfied that they are really broken: you had need call a Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, a great Councel of all the facultys in the polity of man together, for this ſcrutiny; and be aſſured thou ſhalt find thy heart as full of tricks and juggles to keep thee off from calling this Councel, as the Church of Rome put upon the Chriſtian Princes of that age, about calling that councel which proved the Councel of Tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. It was a good time before his holineſs would be preſwaded the Church or Court of Rome needed reformation there was <hi>omnia benè:</hi> Therefore a Councel would be as needleſſe as phyſick to a ſound body: but
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115941:27"/> at laſt to ſtopp the mouth of the loud clamours of the world, a councel is yeilded to: but the time and place kept them in many years debate, to while out the time till they hoped their zeal might cool: but at length called it was, but what was the Iſſue of it? why that councill that was deſigned for a ſcourge of the Church and Court of Rome proved a ſucceſsful engine of its advnacement: ſuch is commonly the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of ſuch great and tumultous aſſemblies, as they are managed by <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>partyes,</hi> So their ordinary product are the dictates of wit, and power; for the moſt part, to the raiſing of the worſt, if not to the ruine of all, as we have but too lately ſeene: but to apply it to our purpoſe. Thou wouldeſt faine bring thy heart to the teſt to try whether it be that broken and mortified humble thing it pretends to. Never expect to find it willing to ſtand the triall. What to be cut and cauterized, to be prob'd and tented, to run through the macerations and martrizations of a thorough examination? It will never endure it, when it comes to the puſh, it will give thee the ſlip if thou doeſt not looke to it: it will uſe all the petty arts imaginable to keep it ſelf from <hi>gaging</hi> and <hi>garb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:</hi> it will tell thee thy heart is a good heart if you can let it alone; there is many a worſe heart that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for a better; is any man but you ſo nice and ſcrupulous, and ſo cruell to his own fleſh (which he ſhould love and cheriſh) as to rake and grable<note place="margin">Eph 5.</note> in his own heart, and to ſeek that in it, which thou wouldeſt be ſorry to finde, and if thou doeſt not finde it, thou wilt be as ſorry thou haſt ſearched it? come let it alone, man thy heart is as good a heart as others are; but ſuppoſe all this fine deluding Rhetorick
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115941:28"/> will not doe, thou ſeeſt a neceſſity of ſearching thy heart to the quick; and art reſolved to ſet upon the work: ſee if the Devil and thine own heart have not ſome trick in lavender, to divert thy moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intentions with ſome plauſible pretences or other, as ſickneſſe, buſineſs, company (<hi>Pol me occidiſtis amici,</hi> is too often true in this caſe of breaking the heart) from breaking the heart. But to make ſhort work with it, as thou muſt doe, if thou wilt make any work at all: If God at laſt ſmite thee by his word or ſword, that thou beginſt to reflect upon thy ſelf, and ſay, ſure I am not in the way to Heaven, that ſtreight and narrow way? I am not ſo ſtrict as I ſhould be for all my heart flatters me thus. And therefore nothing ſhall keepe me from ſearching. Then look for the grandeſt cheat of all: then have a care thy treacherous heart doe not make thee believe, that every little qualm of conſcience is a heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking, every ſleight touch at a Sermon, every heart-ach for any affliction thou feareſt or feeleſt; and when all is done, have a care that thy heart does not out-wit thee at laſt, and that that meanes, which thou uſeſt as the moſt proper expedient to break thy heart, doe not harden it more. O thou doſt not know thine own heart man! It is a cunning and a coſening piece of fleſh; you have a ſtrange ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of this if you need any) in <hi>Hazael, 2 Kin. 11. 12. 13. Eliſha looked upon him ſtedfaſtly till he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamede: and the man of God wept. and</hi> Hazael <hi>ſaid, why weeps my Lord? and he anſwered, becauſe I know the evils that thou ſhalt doe unto the Children of Iſrael.</hi> And when he had told him all his cruelties, he ſhould be guilty of; What ſays <hi>Hazael, Is thy ſervant a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115941:28"/> dogg?</hi> He would not believe his heart was ſo baſe, and yet the man that was ſo much aſhamed that the Prophet ſhould think ſo ill of him, was not aſhamed to be as ill as he thought, and doe as bad as he ſaid. A man would have thought, that that tincture of grace, that dye of ſhame, that ingenuous bluſh which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets eye had caſt upon him, had been the life-bloud of his broken heart that leaped into his face to write his innocence in a dominicall character, that ſeaſonable ſally of modeſty, a man would have thought had been vertues colours: but for all this he was ſo far from a bleeding heart, that he had a bloudy heart: a deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart lead him aſide: he could not fathom the depth<note place="margin">Eſay 44. 20.</note> of his own heart: <hi>The heart of man is deceitfull above all things, and deſperately wicked, who can know it?</hi> Jer. 17. 9. The word which we read, deceitfull, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from whence <hi>Jacob</hi> is derived, that (you know) ſignifies ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planter, and it has two very eminent ſenſes in Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ſignifies crooked, <hi>Eſ. 40. 4. The crooked ſhall be made ſtreight</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Your hearts are crooked hearts, ſerpentine, winding hearts, the crooked ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, you know not where to have them. The way to heaven is too narrow; the gate to life too ſtreight, for ſuch reeling, riddling, crooked pieces.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It ſignifies treacherous <hi>Joſ.</hi> 8. 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Liers in wait.</hi> Your hearts are treacherous hearts and lye in wait to deceive you: your hearts are jugglers, can caſt a miſt before you, and make you think they are broken when they are utterly broke for want of breaking: an ordinary legerdemaine and <hi>deceptio vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> look to it: O it is an unworthy thing for a man to be deceived, but more to be deceived by himſelf, by his own heart, but moſt of all; to be deceived by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115941:29"/> himſelf in ſo neere a concern as the breaking his own heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Remember that God (whoſe eye is in your heart and that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſees what courſe you take to break your hearts: your hearts (as falſe as they are) cannot cheat him: if you doe not paſs a right judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon your hearts, but burne them with a cold Iron, pronounce them broken when they are not bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, God will reverſe your judgment, repeal your ſentence, and break you becauſe you are not broken.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If you be deceived in this point of heart-breaking, you will never thrive in the great work of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: if you judg not aright of your humiliation, you will be miſtaken in the whole work of your ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; I was about to ſay, of your ſalvation, I will ſay of your ſatisfaction. This is the fundamentall work of grace: and it is in grace, as it is in nature, an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in the firſt concoction is not mended in the ſecond,</p>
            <p n="4">4. If you be deceived in this you are deceived for eternity: <hi>the fooliſh virgins were ſo deceived,</hi> and ſo eternally excluded. I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure that would be a great heart-breaking to you to ſee others in the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven</hi> and your ſelves thruſt out. And therfore be ſure, you uſe all the ways to break your hearts, and be ſure, you uſe all the ways to be ſure they are broken, that they may be broken ſo, as that you may goe in <hi>with the Bridegroome,</hi> and not broken becauſe you cannot goe in <hi>with the Bridegroome:</hi> but ſee others goe in and your ſelves kept out. Let us pray therfore to the heart-maker, and to the heart-ſearcher, who is the great heart-breaker that he would give us broken Spirits and contrite hearts, that he would make them ſuch Sacrifices as he will not deſpiſe. <hi>Be it ſo Lord.</hi> Amen Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
